In today's lesson we are going to be diving into classes and constructors, which is
TypeScript's way of modeling real world entities with reasonable blueprints.
We are going to learn how to define a class, initialize it with a constructor and use
access modifiers to control visibility and behaviour.
So first thing, what exactly is a class?
A class is a blueprint for creating objects with shared structure and what exactly is
a class?
A class is a blueprint for creating objects with shared structure and behaviour.
So let's do an example.
So let's build a class of user.
So we use the class keyword here and then define the name and now we just give it the
properties that we want. So we could have, for example, name of string and perhaps is admin.
I'm going to set this boot in and notice after you hover over it, it comes up with this
error message or warning saying property name has no initialiser and not definitely
it assigns in the constructor. So what does that mean? Well, it means that it's expecting
us to provide a value via a constructor for this particular class.
But how do we actually make a constructor? Well, we use the constructor keyword, so constructor
and the constructor takes some parameters. And the parameters that we're going to supply
are the two properties that we need to supply which is name and is admin. So we could have
name of string is admin boolean. So this is now defining our constructor and now we can
just assign the parameter coming in or the value of the parameter coming in and assign
it to our properties, which we do with the keyword called this. So otherwise, how does
it know when we're talking about a name, which names it's talking about, is it talking
about the parameter or the property? Well, you can see it's talking about the parameter.
So in order to target the actual property, we use the keyword this. So this refers to
the actual class constructor or the class itself. So this name equals name. And this is admin
equals is admin. And now a TypeScript is happy that we defined the value. And inside
this class, we can define whatever not only properties, but we can also define various
functions that we want to give to the class. So we could say, for example, greet a function
called greets, which we define as follows as following. We can say just return hello. And
let's just do this as a tactics. So hello, dollar, this dot name. So if the class of user,
we have to find the actual shape, which is specifying the properties and also the behavior
in terms of providing functions and methods. So the constructor sets initial values and the
greet is a method. But how do we actually create an instance of this class? So it comes
here and we can do const Alice equals, and we give the keyword new. So this is creates
a new instance of the actual class. So a new user. And now we have to find the values
for our parameters. So we can say Alice. And we can say Alice is admin. And then of course
we can actually call the behavior by doing so console log. And say Alice greet. Let's
now run this and we get a console message over here saying hello Alice. The moments
we have this way of assigning the value coming in by the parameter straight to the property
defined on the class. And we're doing with this keyword this, but there's actually a short
time way of doing that. So what we can do is we can actually create a property and the
parameter at the same time by to declare the parameters as public. So what we do is we
can remove the internal properties here, remove the assignment, and we put public in front
of this and public in front of the property here. And this by putting public here, it automatically
does the same thing by creating a property and assigning the value from the parameter coming
in all in one hit. So by doing this like this, we have a very short and precise construct
for doing the constructor. Okay, so next we want to talk about access modifiers. Let's
say for example that you want to have some properties, but you want to control the visibility
of these properties to other classes in your code or any other code running in externally.
So how can we do this? Well, we're just going to undo what we have here so I can demonstrate.
So let's say for example that we want to have the name is public, but this here is private.
Now the default access modifier is public, which means all of these are visible to other
codes. Now if we can also explicitly put the word public in front of this, and this property
now becomes public, but the one underneath we can say for example private. That means
we are on able to execute that or access that outside the class. We come into here and
try and access the is admin property. Notice we don't have it available. And that's because
we've marked it now as private, which means it's only visible to any methods inside
the class. And as soon as we come out here, it's no longer visible. Of course, if I want
to make it public, I can just change that back to public again. And we should be able to
come to here and we can see how access to that property. But as I said, that the public
is the default. So we don't actually have to explicitly set it to public. We can actually
come in here that it's still visible to us. But we can also set this to read only as well.
So let's say, for example, that we want to change this to be read only. We could, I'm
in here and specify that as read only. Now, we are able to set the value of the is admin
flag when we actually call the constructor. That's fine. But if we try to change the value
outside, so if we do Alice, and say as is admin equals false, then we're going to get
an error because we are trying to change a read only property. So again, as a recap, read
only properties can only be set via the constructor. You can't then set them afterwards.
So inside our class, we can start to build up some some conditional logic. Let me show
you what I mean. So if we come into here and let's say we create a class called an account,
we're going to have a constructor, we're going to use the shorthand way of finding
some properties. So public username string. And let's have a balance or bank account. And
we can automatically, and we can put the word private to say that it's going to create
a private property called balance. We can have empty constructor. And now we can have a method
called withdraw, where we specify the amount as a number. And this returns a string, which
is going to be whether it's successful or not. And now we can put some conditional insight
here. So we could say, for example, if the amount is greater than the property of the
balance, which is now being defined, I'm here as past the constructor. So via this short
time, the way of doing it, then we can say, for example, just return insufficient upon
this. If it's not the case, and we have enough balance, we can have our balance and we
can reduce it by the amount coming in. Let's return a message saying, say, let's do new
balance, specify this dot balance. So when we're defining class, we can also as any logic,
we want inside that class. So let's imagine we want to model a bank account. So we could
do, for example, account. And we can have a constructor. And we're going to find some properties
using the short hand way of doing it. So we can say public username. We have that as a string.
We have a constructor. And we can use the short hand way of doing that. So we could have
a property called username, which is a string. And we can have a balance on the account and
we can use the private way. So we can't access it outside the class. Let's have a property
called balance and set that to number. And then we have an empty constructor. We can now
to find some behavior. So we could try and rip draw some money from the account. Let's
pass in the amounts we want to have draw. And we want to return a string with a message
whether we're successful or not. And now we can do some logic inside this. So we can
check that the amount is greater than the internal balance, which is defined as a property
here. And if it is, we can then return a message saying in sufficient funds. Otherwise we
are have enough balance and we can just reduce the balance by the amount. And then return
the new balance and say this dot balance. So this is a form of what's called encapsulation
because encapsulations letting us protect internal states and we're protecting the actual
property balance here and expose safe methods. So the caller can only access the balance
via this method here. And hence why encapsulation is a very good practice for building into
your classes. Now we talked about a number of things and one of the other things we can do
on our class is we can set some properties and some default values. So let's say we have
a class of point. And the class of point is going to have a couple of properties. We could
have X. And what we can do is we can set it to a value initially. So we can set X to 0. And
then TypeScript is going to understand straight away that this is a number because we've
initialized it with a value. And we can do Y and set that to 0 for example. But alternatively
we can also specify the default values in the constructor. So we could have X and set this
type as number. We're going to Y set this type as number. Then we could have a constructor
and we can say X defaults to 0 when it's passed in on Y defaults to 0. Then we can just
do it this way. We wanted to and say this equals X. And this dot Y equals Y. And then
of course it's going to set it to 0. And we could also use the shortcut way of doing
it as well if you prefer that. Now classes are pretty critical to understand when doing
type strits because it's going to be using them an awful lot when you're actually doing
developments. So classes pretty much let us bundle and not only structure but also behavior
into reusable blueprints.